So when I was a kid ...
عندما كنت صغيرا
this was my team.
كان هذا فريقي .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I stunk at sports.
أهتميت بالرياضة .
I didn't like to play them, I didn't like to watch them.
لم ارغب في أن العابهم أو اشاهدهم.
So this is what I did. I went fishing.
ما أردت فعله ، أردت الصيد .
And for all of my growing up I fished on the shores of Connecticut,
شبيت في بلدي وأنا اصطاد على شواطئ ولاية كونيتيكت،
and these are the creatures that I saw on a regular basis.
وهذه هي المخلوقات التي رأيتها على أساس منتظم.
But after I grew up and went to college,
ولكن بعد بلوغي وذهابي الى الكلية ،
and I came home in the early 90's,
وبعد عودتي للمنزل في بدايات التسعينات،
this is what I found.
هذا ما وجدته .
My team had shrunk.
لقد تقلص فريقي .
It was like literally having your roster devastated.
أنه مثل وجود قائمة قد دمرت حرفيا .
And as I sort of looked into that,
وكما قلت من يتطلع إلى ذلك،
from a very personal point of view as a fisherman,
من وجهة نظري كصياد،
I started to kind of figure out,
بدأ نوع من المعرفة،
well, what was the rest of the world thinking about it?
حسنا، كيف كان يفكر بقية العالم في هذا ؟
First place I started to look was fish markets.
نظرت أولا الى اسواق الأسماك.
And when I went to fish markets,
وعندما ذهبت اليها،
in spite of where I was --
وعلى الرغم من أين كنت
whether I was in North Carolina, or Paris, or London, or wherever --
سواء كنت في شمال كارولينا، باريس أو لندن،
I kept seeing this weirdly repeating trope of four creatures,
ظللت أرى بغرابة اربعة من المخلوقات،
again and again --
مرارا وتكرارا .
on the menus, on ice --
في قائمة الطعام ، على الثلج ،
shrimp, tuna, salmon and cod.
جمبري، تونة، سالمون وسمك القد
And I thought this was pretty strange,
أعتقد أن هذا غريب جدا،
and as I looked at it, I was wondering,
وعندما كنت انظر اليهم كنت اتساءل،
did anyone else notice this sort of shrinking of the market?
هل لاحظ احد غيري هذا التقلص في حجم السوق ؟
Well, when I looked into it,
عندما نظرت في ذلك،
I realized that people didn't look at it as their team.
أدركت أن الناس لم ينظروا اليها على انهم فريقهم.
Ordinary people, the way they looked at seafood was like this.
الناس العاديين، هيئتهم في المأكولات البحرية كانت مثل هذا.
It's not an unusual human characteristic
انها ليست سمة الإنسان غير العادية
to reduce the natural world down to very few elements.
الحد من العالم الطبيعي وصولا الى الحد الأقل من العناصر.
We did it before, 10,000 years ago, when we came out of our caves.
فعلنا ذلك من قبل، 10،000 سنة مضت، عندما خرجنا
If you look at fire pits from 10,000 years ago,
اذا نظرتم الى حفريات النار من 10،000 سنة مضت،
you'll see raccoons, you'll see, you know, wolves,
سترون الراكون، الذئاب،
you'll see all kinds of different creatures.
سوف ترون كل الأنواع المختلفة من المخلوقات.
But if you telescope to the age of -- you know, 2,000 years ago,
واذا نظرتم قبل 2000 عام،
you'll see these four mammals:
سترون هذة الثديات الأربعة:
pigs, cows, sheep and goats.
الخنازير، الأبقار، الخرفان والماعز.
It's true of birds, too.
من الطيور ايضا
You look at the menus in New York City restaurants
اذا نظرتم الى القوائم في لمطاعم مدينة نيويورك
150 years ago, 200 years ago,
منذ 150 الى 200 عام مضت ،
you'll see snipe, woodcock, grouse, dozens of ducks, dozens of geese.
سترون طيور الشنقب، ودكوك، الدجاج البري وعشرات من البط.
But telescope ahead to the age of modern animal husbandry,
وبنظرة تليسكوبية الى عصر تربية الحيوانات الحديثة،
and you'll see four:
سترون اربعة :
turkeys, ducks, chicken and geese.
الديك الرومي والبط والدجاج والأوز.
So it makes sense that we've headed in this direction.
لذلك فمن المنطقي أن نتوجه في هذا الاتجاه.
But how have we headed in this direction?
ولكن كيف وقد توجهنا في هذا الاتجاه؟
Well ...
حسنا...
first it's a very, very new problem.
اولا تلك مشكلة جديدة .
This is the way we've been fishing the oceans over the last 50 years.
تلك هى الطريقة التي نصطاد بها من المحيطات منذ 50 عاما
World War II was a tremendous incentive to arm ourselves in a war against fish.
كانت الحرب العالمية الثانية حافزا هائلا لتسليح انفسنا
All of the technology that we perfected during World War II --
كل التكنولوجيات التي أوجدناها اثناء الحرب العالمية الثانية
sonar, lightweight polymers --
السونار، البوليمرات خفيفة الوزن
all these things were redirected towards fish.
كل هذه الأشياء تم إعادة توجيهها نحو الأسماك.
And so you see this tremendous buildup in fishing capacity,
ولهذا ترى هذا الحشد الهائل في قدرات الصيد،
quadrupling in the course of time,
أربعة أضعاف في مجرى الزمن،
from the end of World War II to the present time.
من نهاية الحرب العالمية الثانية الى الوقت الحالي.
And right now that means
هذا يعني
we're taking between 80 and 90 million metric tons out of the sea every year.
اننا نستخرج مابين 80 الى 90 مليون طن من التونة
That's the equivalent of the human weight of China
وهذا يعادل الوزن البشري في الصين
taken out of the sea every year.
يستخرج من البحر كل عام.
And it's no coincidence that I use China as the example
وليس من قبيل الصدفة ان نستخدم الصين في المثال
because China is now the largest fishing nation in the world.
لأن الصين هي اكبر أمة صيادة في العالم .
Well, that's only half the story.
تلك هي نصف القصة .
The other half of the story
النصف الاخر
is this incredible boom in fish farming and aquaculture,
ان هناك الطفرة لا تصدق في تربية الأسماك وتربية الأحياء المائية،
which is now, only in the last year or two,
فقط في العام أو العامين الماضيين،
starting to exceed the amount of wild fish that we produce.
بدأت تتجاوز الأسماك البرية التي ننتجها.
So that if you add wild fish and farmed fish together,
بحيث إذا قمت بإضافة الأسماك البرية والأسماك المستزرعة معا،
you get the equivalent of two Chinas created from the ocean
يمكنك الحصول على ما يعادل صينين من المحيط
each and every year.
كل عام .
And again, it's not a coincidence that I use China as the example,
ومرة أخرى، فإنه ليس من قبيل الصدفة ان نستخدم الصين باعتبارها
because China, in addition to being the biggest catcher of fish,
اكبر صائد للأسماك،
is also the biggest farmer of fish.
وايضا اكبر مستزرع للأسماك .
So let's look though at the four choices we are making right now.
لذلك دعونا ننظر من خلال الخيارات الأربعة.
The first one --
اولا :
by far the most consumed seafood in America and in much of the West,
حتى الآن المأكولات البحرية الأكثر استهلاكا في أمريكا
is shrimp.
الجمبري
Shrimp in the wild -- as a wild product --
الجمبري منتج بري
is a terrible product.
هو منتج رهيب.
5, 10, 15 pounds of wild fish are regularly killed
5، 10، 15 رطلا من الأسماك البرية يقتلون بانتظام
to bring one pound of shrimp to the market.
لجلب جنيه واحد من الجمبري إلى السوق.
They're also incredibly fuel inefficient to bring to the market.
كما أنها وقود غير فعال في الأسواق
In a recent study that was produced out of Dalhousie University,
في دراسة حديثة خرجت من جامعة دالهوزي،
it was found that dragging for shrimp
وجدوا ان الجمبري
is one of the most carbon-intensive ways of fishing that you can find.
هي واحدة من أكثر الكربونات الكثيفة التي يمكنك اصطيادها
So you can farm them,
لذا يمكن زراعتها،
and people do farm them,
وبالفعل يقوم الناس بزراعته،
and they farm them a lot in this very area.
وكانوا يزرعون منها الكثير بالذات.
Problem is ...
المشكلة هى
the place where you farm shrimp is in these wild habitats --
الأماكن التي يتم فيها استزراع الجمبري في البرية
in mangrove forests.
في غابات المنجروف .
Now look at those lovely roots coming down.
انظروا الي تلك الجذور النازلة .
Those are the things that hold soil together,
تلك هي الأشياء التي تربط التربة معا،
protect coasts, create habitats for all sorts of young fish, young shrimp,
تحمي السواحل، وتخلق مواطن لجميع أنواع الأسماك الصغيرة والجمبري
all sorts of things that are important to this environment.
كل أنواع الأشياء التي تعتبر مهمة لهذه البيئة.
Well, this is what happens to a lot of coastal mangrove forests.
حسنا، هذا هو ما يحدث إلى الكثير من غابات المنغروف الساحلية.
We've lost millions of acres of coastal mangroves
فقدنا ملايين الأفدنة من أشجار المنجروف الساحلية
over the last 30 or 40 years.
على مدى 30 أو 40 عاما .
That rate of destruction has slowed,
وقد تباطأ هذا المعدل،
but we're still in a major mangrove deficit.
ولكن نحن لا نزال لدينا عجز كبير في المنغروف.
The other thing that's going on here
والشيء الآخر هنا
is a phenomenon that the filmmaker Mark Benjamin called "Grinding Nemo."
هى ظاهرة صانع الأفلام مارك بينجامين يطلق عليها "الطحن"
This phenomenon is very, very relevant
تلك الظاهرة مرتبطة جدا
to anything that you've ever seen on a tropical reef.
بشيء لم تراه في أي وقت مضى على الشعاب المرجانية الاستوائية.
Because what's going on right now,
لأن ما يحدث الآن،
we have shrimp draggers dragging for shrimp,
لدينا سحب للجمبري،
catching a huge amount of bycatch,
بأصطياد كمية كبيرة منه،
that bycatch in turn gets ground up and turned into shrimp food.
ما يحدث أن الصيد العرضي بدوره يتحول إلى غذاء الجمبري
And sometimes, many of these vessels --
وأحيانا، كثير من هذه السفن
manned by slaves --
يعمل بها عبيد
are catching these so-called "trash fish,"
ويتم اصطياد ما يسمى "الأسماك القمامة"
fish that we would love to see on a reef,
الأسماك التي نحب رؤيتها في الشعاب المرجانية،
grinding them up
يطحنوها
and turning them into shrimp feed --
ويحولوها الى علف للجمبري
an ecosystem literally eating itself and spitting out shrimp.
نظام بيئي يأكل نفسه حرفيا ويبصق الجمبري.
The next most consumed seafood in America,
التالي الذي يعتبر من المأكولات البحرية الأكثر استهلاكا في أمريكا،
and also throughout the West,
وايضا عبر الغرب،
is tuna.
التونة.
So tuna is this ultimate global fish.
حتى التونة تلك الأسماك العالمية في نهاية المطاف.
These huge management areas have to be observed
يجب مراعتها أداريا
in order for tuna to be well managed.
من أجل أن تدار بشكل جيد.
Our own management area,
في منطقتنا الأدارية،
called a Regional Fisheries Management Organization,
والمسماة "المنظمة الأقليمية لمصائد الأسماك"
is called ICCAT,
وتسى اختصارا ICCAT،
the International Commission for the Conservation of Atlantic Tunas.
اللجنة الدولية للحفاظ على التونة في الأطلسي.
The great naturalist Carl Safina once called it,
عالم الطبيعيات الكبير كارل سافينا دعاه ذات مرة،
"The International Conspiracy to Catch all the Tunas."
" المؤامرة الدولية لاصطياد كل أسماك التونة "
Of course we've seen incredible improvement
بالطبع رأينا تحسن لا يصدق في
in ICCAT in the last few years,
ICCAT في السنوات القليلة الماضية،
there is total room for improvement,
هناك مجالا للتحسين،
but it remains to be said that tuna is a global fish,
ولكن يبقى أن يقال أن التونة سمكة العالمية،
and to manage it, we have to manage the globe.
وللسيطرة عليها علينا السيطرة على العالم.
Well, we could also try to grow tuna
يمكن ايضا تربية التونة
but tuna is a spectacularly bad animal for aquaculture.
ولكن التونة سيئة بشكل مذهل للمزارع السمكية
Many people don't know this but tuna are warm-blooded.
العديد لا يعلم ذلك لكن التونة من ذوات الدم الدافئ
They can heat their bodies 20 degrees above ambient temperature,
يمكن أن تيد حرارتها بمقدار 20 درجة اعلى من حرارة الغرفة،
they can swim at over 40 miles an hour.
يمكنها أن تسبح بسرعة 40 ميل في الساعة.
So that pretty much eliminates
بحيث يزيل مقدار كبير
all the advantages of farming a fish, right?
من مزايا استزراع الأسماك، أليس كذلك؟
A farmed fish is --
الأسماك المستزرعة
or a fish is cold-blooded, it doesn't move too much.
من ذوات الدم البارد والتي لا تتحرك كثيرا.
That's a great thing for growing protein.
وهذا شئ جيد لزيادة نسبة البروتين فيها.
But if you've got this crazy, wild creature
ولكن إذا حصلت على هذا المجنون، مخلوق البرية
that swims at 40 miles an hour and heats its blood --
الذي يسبح بسرعة 40 ميل في الساعة ويسخن دمه
not a great candidate for aquaculture.
فهو ليس مرشح لاستزراعه سمكيا.
The next creature --
المخلوق التالي
most consumed seafood in America and throughout the West --
لأكثر استهلاكا علي مائدة المأكولات البحرية في أمريكا وعلى طول الغرب
is salmon.
السالمون .
Now salmon got its plundering, too,
الآن السلمون يحدث له نهب، أيضا،
but it didn't really necessarily happen through fishing.
ولكن ليس من الضروري حدوثه بواسطة الصيد،
This is my home state of Connecticut.
تلك ولايتي كونيتيكت.
Connecticut used to be home to a lot of wild salmon.
كونيتكيت موطن الكثير من السالمون .
But if you look at this map of Connecticut,
ولكن اذا نظرت الى خريطة الولاية،
every dot on that map is a dam.
كل نقطة هى عبارة عن سد .
There are over 3,000 dams in the state of Connecticut.
هناك اكثر من 3000 سد في الولاية
I often say this is why people in Connecticut are so uptight --
ودائما ما أقول أن هذا هو السبب الذي يجعل الناس في الولاية متوترون جدا -
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If somebody could just unblock Connecticut's chi,
إذا استطاع شخص ما فقط الافراج عن تشي كونيكتيكت،
I feel that we could have an infinitely better world.
أشعر أنه يمكن أن نصبح عالم أفضل بكثير.
But I made this particular comment
ولكن جعلت هذا التعليق
at a convention once of national parks officers,
في اتفاقية موظفي الحدائق الوطنية،
and this guy from North Carolina sidled up to me, he says,
وهذا الرجل من ولاية كارولينا الشمالية ، يقول:
"You know, you oughtn't be so hard on your Connecticut,
"اتعلم انه من الصعب الا يكون في كونتكيت،
cause we here in North Carolina, we got 35,000 dams."
لأنه لدينا هنا في شمال كارولينا 35000 سدا
So it's a national epidemic, it's an international epidemic.
انها وباء وطني، بل وباء عالمي.
And there are dams everywhere,
هناك سدود في كل مكان،
and these are precisely the things
وهذه هي بالضبط الأشياء
that stop wild salmon from reaching their spawning grounds.
التي تمنع السالمون من الوصول الى مناطق التكاثر.
So as a result, we've turned to aquaculture,
وكنتيجة لذلك يجب علينا استزراعها سمكيا،
and salmon is one the most successful, at least from a numbers point of view.
والسالمون من انجح الاسماك لعدة نقاط
When they first started farming salmon,
عندما بدأت لأول مرة زراعة سمك السلمون،
it could take as many as six pounds of wild fish
قد يستغرق ما يصل ستة باوندات من السمك البرية
to make a single pound of salmon.
لعمل رطل واحد من سمك السلمون.
The industry has, to its credit, greatly improved.
الصناعة تحسنت كثيرا.
They've gotten it below two to one,
لقد حصلت على أدناه 2 الى1،
although it's a little bit of a cheat
على الرغم من وجود قليل من الغش
because if you look at the way aquaculture feed is produced,
لأنه إذا نظرتم الى الطريقة التي يتم إنتاج الأعلاف للمزارع السمكية،
they're measuring pellets --
يقيسون الكريات
pounds of pellets per pound of salmon.
باوند من الكريات لكل باوند من السالمون .
Those pellets are in turn reduced fish.
تلك الكريات بدورها تخفض الأسماك.
So the actual -- what's called the FIFO, the fish in and the fish out --
وبالتالي فإن ما يحدث - ما يسمى FIFO، السمكة داخلة وسمكة خارجة -
kind of hard to say.
من الصعب القول.
But in any case,
ولكن على اية حال،
credit to the industry,
مفخرة لهذه الصناعة
it has lowered the amount of fish per pound of salmon.
فقد خفضت كمية الأسماك لكل رطل من سمك السالمون.
Problem is we've also gone crazy
المشكلة تقودنا الى الجنون
with the amount of salmon that we're producing.
مع كمية السالمون المنتجة .
Aquaculture is the fastest growing food system on the planet.
مزارع الاسماك اسرع نظام غذائي ينمو على وجه الارض .
It's growing at something like seven percent per year.
تنمو بمقدار 7% في العام .
And so even though we're doing less per fish
على الرغم من قلة الاسماك
to bring it to the market,
الموجودة في الأسواق،
we're still killing a lot of these little fish.
ما زلنا نقتل الاسماك الصغيرة.
And it's not just fish that we're feeding fish to,
ليست الاسماك فقط بل ما نطعمه الاسماك،
we're also feeding fish to chickens and pigs.
نحن نُطعم الاسماك للدجاج والخنازير.
So we've got chickens and they're eating fish,
فنحصل على دجاج يتغذى على الاسماك،
but weirdly, we also have fish that are eating chickens.
وللغرابة، السمك يتغذى على الدجاج .
Because the byproducts of chickens -- feathers, blood, bone --
لأن مشتقات الدجاج الريش ،الدم والعظام
get ground up and fed to fish.
تغذى بها الاسماك.
So I often wonder,
لطالما تسألت،
is there a fish that ate a chicken that ate a fish?
هل هناك سمكة تأكل دجاجة تغذت على سمكة؟
It's sort of a reworking of the chicken and egg thing. Anyway --
انها نوع من إعادة صياغة بين الدجاجة والبيضة .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
All together, though, it results in a terrible mess.
كل ذلك معا، على الرغم من أنه يؤدي إلى فوضى رهيبة.
What you're talking about
ما نتحدث عنه؟
is something between 20 and 30 million metric tons of wild creatures
هو شئ بين 20 الى 30 مليون طن من المخلوقات البرية
that are taken from the ocean and used and ground up.
نستخرجها من المحيط ونستخدمها.
That's the equivalent of a third of a China,
وهذا ما يعادل ثلث الصين،
or of an entire United States of humans
أو الولايات المتحدة بأكملها من البشر
that's taken out of the sea each and every year.
يستخرج من البحر كل عام .
The last of the four is a kind of amorphous thing.
اما أخر الأربعة انواع ،
It's what the industry calls "whitefish."
ما يطلق عليها صناعياً "السمك الأبيض".
There are many fish that get cycled into this whitefish thing
هناك العديد من الأسماك يتم تدويرها الى السمك الأبيض
but the way to kind of tell the story, I think,
ولكن طريقة معرفة القصة، كما أعتقد،
is through that classic piece of American culinary innovation,
من خلال هذه القطعة الكلاسيكية من ابتكار الطاهي الأمريكي،
the Filet-O-Fish sandwich.
سندوتشات سمك الفيليه .
So the Filet-O-Fish sandwich actually started as halibut.
بدأت سندوتشات سمك الفيليه من سمكة الهلبوت.
And it started because a local franchise owner
وبدأت لصاحب الامتياز المحلي
found that when he served his McDonald's on Friday, nobody came.
الذي وجد أنه عندما خدم في ماكدونالد يوم الجمعة لم يأتي احد .
Because it was a Catholic community, they needed fish.
لأنه كان مجتمع كاثوليكي، يحتاج للأسماك.
So he went to Ray Kroc and he said,
حتى انه ذهب الى راي كروك وقال:
"I'm going to bring you a fish sandwich, going to be made out of halibut."
"سأذهب لأحضر لك سندويتش السمك، سيكون مصنوع من سمكة الهلبوت
Ray Kroc said, "I don't think it's going to work.
راى كروك قال " لا أعتقد انها ستنجح.
I want to do a Hula Burger,
أريد أن اصنع هولا برجر،
and there's going to be a slice of pineapple on a bun.
وسيكون هناك شريحة من الأناناس على الكعكة.
But let's do this, let's have a bet.
ولكن فلنفعلها فلنجرب حظنا.
Whosever sandwich sells more, that will be the winning sandwich."
ستبيع اكثر وستكون الشطيرة الفائزة."
Well, it's kind of sad for the ocean that the Hula Burger didn't win.
انه لمن المحزن للمحيطات أن هولا برغر لم تنجح.
So he made his halibut sandwich.
لذا فقد صنع له شطيرة الهلبوت.
Unfortunately though, the sandwich came in at 30 cents.
للأسف رغم ذلك، جاءت الشطيرة ب 30 سنتا.
Ray wanted the sandwich to come in at 25 cents,
ارادها راي ب 25 سنتا
so he turned to Atlantic cod.
لذلك التفت إلى القد الأطلسي.
We all know what happened to Atlantic cod in New England.
نحن جميعا نعرف ما حدث لسمك القد الأطلسي في نيو انغلاند.
So now the Filet-O-Fish sandwich is made out of Alaska pollock,
وحتى الآن ساندويتش فيليه السمك يصنع من بولوك ألاسكا،
it's the largest fin fish fishery in the United States,
انها من أكبر الأسماك ذات الزعنفة في الولايات المتحدة،
2 to 3 billion pounds of fish taken out of the sea every single year.
يستخرج من 2 الى 3 مليون من البحر سنويا.
If we go through the pollock,
اذا ذهبنا من خلال بولوك،
the next choice is probably going to be tilapia.
الخيار القادم هو على الارجح سيكون البلطي.
Tilapia is one of those fish nobody ever heard of 20 years ago.
البلطي من تلك الأسماك التي لم يسمع بها قبل 20 عاما.
It's actually a very efficient converter of plant protein into animal protein,
انها في الواقع تحويل فعال جدا من البروتينات النباتية في الحيوان
and it's been a godsend to the third world.
انها هبة من السماء إلى العالم الثالث.
It's actually a tremendously sustainable solution,
في الواقع وبشكل كبير هى حل مستدام،
it goes from an egg to an adult in nine months.
فهى تتحول من البيضة للبلوغ في تسعة اشهر.
The problem is that when you look about the West,
والمشكلة هي أنه عندما ننظر للغرب،
it doesn't do what the West wants it to do.
فإنه لا يفعل ما يريد الغرب أن يفعله.
It really doesn't have what's called an oily fish profile.
انه حقا لايوجد ما يسمى ملف تعريف الأسماك الزيتية.
It doesn't have the EPA and DHA omega-3s
ليس لديها EPA و DHA أوميجا-3S
that we all think are going to make us live forever.
نعتقد جميعا اننا نسير لتجعلنا نعيش إلى الأبد.
So what do we do?
فماذا نفعل؟
I mean, first of all, what about this poor fish, the clupeids?
اعني اول شيء بالنسبة للسمك الفقير؟
The fish that represent a huge part of that 20 to 30 million metric tons.
السمك الذي يمثل الجزء الأكبر من 20 الى 30 مليون طن
Well, one possibility that a lot of conservationists have raised
حسنا، احتمال واحد أن الكثير من دعاة حماية البيئة أثاروا
is could we eat them?
ايمكننا أن نأكلهم ؟
Could we eat them directly instead of feeding them to salmon?
ايمكننا أن نأكلها بدلا من أن نطعمها للسالمون ؟
There are arguments for it.
هناك حجج لذلك.
They are tremendously fuel efficient to bring to market,
هى تشكل كفاءة كبيرة في استهلاك الوقود لطرحها في السوق،
a fraction of the fuel cost of say, shrimp,
جزء صغير من تكلفة الوقود الجمبري،
and at the very top of the carbon efficiency scale.
وعلى القمة في مقياس الكفاءة الكربوني.
They also are omega-3 rich, a great source for EPA and DHA.
وغنية ايضا بأوميغا 3 ، ومصدر كبير للEPA و DHA.
So that is a potential.
لذلك هذا هو المحتمل.
And if we were to go down that route what I would say is,
وإذا كان لنا أن نذهب في هذا الطريق ما أود أن أقوله هو،
instead of paying a few bucks a pound -- or a few bucks a ton, really --
بدلا من دفع بضعة دولارات للرطل أو بضعة دولارات للطن،
and making it into aquafeed,
وجعله علف مائي،
could we halve the catch and double the price for the fishermen
يمكننا خفض الصيد ومضاعفة السعر للصيادين
and make that our way of treating these particular fish?
ونجعلها طريقتنا لعلاج هذه الأسماك بعينها؟
Other possibility though, which is much more interesting,
إمكانية أخرى من خلال، وهي مثيرة للاهتمام بشكل كبير،
is looking at bivalves, particularly mussels.
نبحث في ذوات الصدفتين، ولا سيما بلح البحر.
Now, mussels are very high in EPA and DHA, they're similar to canned tuna.
بلح البحر به نسبة مرتفعة من EPA و DHA، مشابهة لسمك التونة المعلبة.
They're also extremely fuel efficient.
انها أيضا وقود ذو كفاءة.
To bring a pound of mussels to market
لأحضار رطل من محار البحر الى الأسواق
is about a thirtieth of the carbon as required to bring beef to market.
حوالي 1/30 من الكربون كما هو مطلوب لجعل لحوم البقر
They require no forage fish,
لأنها لا تحتاج إلى العلف السمكي،
they actually get their omega-3s by filtering the water of microalgae.
في الواقع تحصل على أوميغا 3S من خلال تصفية المياه
In fact, that's where omega-3s come from, they don't come from fish.
هذا هو المكان الذي تأتي أوميغا 3S منه، أنها لا تأتي من الأسماك.
Microalgae make the omega-3s, they're only bioconcentrated in fish.
الطحالب جعلت اوميغا 3 تتركز أحيائيا فقط في الأسماك.
Mussels and other bivalves
بلح البحر وذوات الصدفتين
do tremendous amounts of water filtration.
يقوم بتنقية كميات هائلة من المياه.
A single mussel can filter dozens of gallons every single day.
ويمكن لبلحة بحر واحدة تصفية عشرات الغالونات في اليوم الواحد.
And this is incredibly important when we look at the world.
وهذا أمر مهم للغاية عندما ننظر إلى العالم.
Right now, nitrification, overuse of phosphates in our waterways
الآن، النترجة، الإفراط بستخدام الفوسفات بالممرات المائية
are causing tremendous algal blooms.
تسبب في تكاثر هائل للطحالب .
Over 400 new dead zones have been created in the last 20 years,
أكثر من 400 من المناطق الميتة الجديدة تم إنشاؤها في السنوات ال 20 الماضية،
tremendous sources of marine life death.
مصادر هائلة من الحياة البحرية.
We also could look at not a fish at all.
نحن أيضا يمكن ألا ننظر الى السمك على الإطلاق.
We could look at a vegetable.
يمكن أن ننظر الى الخضروات.
We could look at seaweed, the kelps,
يمكننا أن ننظر إلى الأعشاب البحرية
all these different varieties of things that can be high in omega-3s,
كل هذه الأنواع المختلفة من الأشياء يمكن أن تكون غنية بأوميغا 3S،
can be high in proteins,
والبروتينات،
tremendously good things.
من الأشياء الجيدة جدا ايضا.
They filter the water just like mussels do.
تصفية المياه تماما مثل بلح البحر .
And weirdly enough,
بما فيه الكفاية
it turns out that you can actually feed this to cows.
واتضح أنه يمكن تغذيتها للأبقار.
Now, I'm not a big fan of cattle.
أنا لست معجب كبير بالماشية.
But if you wanted to keep growing cattle
ولكن إن كنت تريد بقاء الماشية في زيادة
in a time and place where water resources are limited,
في الزمان والمكان حيث الموارد المائية محدودة،
you're growing seaweed in the water, you don't have to water it --
زد من الطحالب في الماء، ليس عليك أن تسقيها،
major consideration.
اعتبار رئيسي.
And the last fish is a question mark.
والأسماك الأخيرة هي علامة استفهام.
We have the ability to create aquacultured fish
لدينا القدرة لتربية اسماك مستزرعة
that creates a net gain of marine protein for us.
والذي بدوره يوفّر لنا البروتين .
This creature would have to be vegetarian,
أن هذا المخلوق يجب أن يكون نباتي،
it would have to be fast growing,
ينمو بسرعة،
it would have to be adaptable to a changing climate
قابل للتكيف مع التغيرات المناخية
and it would have to have that oily fish profile,
ولديه ما لدى الأسماك من
that EPA, DHA, omega-3 fatty acid profile that we're looking for.
أن EPA، DHA، اوميجا 3 الدهنية الأحماض التي نبحث عنها.
This exists kind of on paper.
وهذا النوع من الورق موجود.
I have been reporting on these subjects for 15 years.
لقد تم الإبلاغ عن هذه الموضوعات لمدة 15 عاما.
Every time I do a new story, somebody tells me,
كل مرة احكيها يخبرني شخص
"We can do all that. We can do it. We've figured it all out.
"يمكننا أن نفعل كل هذا . يمكننا القيام به. عرفنا كيف نفعله.
We can produce a fish
نحن يمكن ان ننتج الأسماك
that's a net gain of marine protein and has omega-3s."
هذا ربح صافي من البروتين البحري ويحتوي على أوميغا 3S ".
Great.
عظيم.
It doesn't seem to be getting scaled up.
ولكن لا يتم توسيع نطاقها.
It is time to scale this up.
حان الوقت لتوسيع نطاقها
If we do,
اذا فعلنا،
30 million metric tons of seafood, a third of the world catch,
30 مليون طن متري من المأكولات البحرية، ثلث الصيد العالمي،
stays in the water.
سيبقى في الماء .
So I guess what I'm saying is this is what we've been going with.
لذلك أعتقد أن ما أقوله هو هذا هو ما يمكننا المضي به.
We tend to go with our appetites rather than our minds.
نحن نميل إلى الذهاب مع شهيتنا بدلا من عقولنا.
But if we went with this, or some configuration of it,
ولكن إذا مضينا مع هذا، أو بعض الاعدادات من ذلك،
we might have a little more of this.
قد يكون لدينا أكثر قليلا من هذا.
Thank you.
شكرا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)